<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the consecration of the Right Reverend Fathers in God, Gilbert Lord Bishop of London, Humphry Lord Bishop of Sarum, George Lord Bishop of Worcester, Robert Lord Bishop of Lincolne, George Lord Bishop of St. Asaph. On Sunday 28. October, 1660. at S. Peters Westminster. By John Sudbury, one of the prebendaries of that church.</title>
            <author>Sudbury, John, 1604-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6136</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1048_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203686</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863547</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863547</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94109)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 155:E1048[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the consecration of the Right Reverend Fathers in God, Gilbert Lord Bishop of London, Humphry Lord Bishop of Sarum, George Lord Bishop of Worcester, Robert Lord Bishop of Lincolne, George Lord Bishop of St. Asaph. On Sunday 28. October, 1660. at S. Peters Westminster. By John Sudbury, one of the prebendaries of that church.</title>
                  <author>Sudbury, John, 1604-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Royston, at the Angel in Ivie-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novemb 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sheldon, Gilbert, 1598-1677 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Henchman, Humphrey, 1592-1675 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Morley, George, 1597-1684 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sanderson, Robert, 1587-1663 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Griffith, George, 1601-1666 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Consecration of bishops --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115751:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON <hi>PREACHED</hi> At the Conſecration of the Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Fathers in God,
<list>
                  <item>GILBERT <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> London,</item>
                  <item>HUMPHRY <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Sarum,</item>
                  <item>GEORGE <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Worceſter,</item>
                  <item>ROBERT <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Lincolne,</item>
                  <item>GEORGE <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> St. Aſaph.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>On Sunday 28. <hi>October,</hi> 1660. at S. <hi>Peters WESTMINSTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By JOHN SUDBURY, One of the Prebendaries of that Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Ivie-lane,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115751:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115751:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>EDVVARD Lord HYDE,</hi> Baron of <hi>Henden,</hi> Lord high Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi> Chancellor of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> one of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſent this Sermon to the Preſs in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, I have taken the boldneſs to ſhelter it under the protection of Your Name; in hope that when the Readers ſhall ſee it hath had <hi>Your</hi> approbation, they will be the better inclined to afford it their own. I wiſh it may have this effect upon ſuch as have any prejudice againſt the Truth, which I aſſert and maintain; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:115751:3"/>it is of ſo much concernment to the publick good, that I cannot think it would have any Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but ſuch as are the enemies of Mankind, if it were not through ſome miſ-underſtanding, which I have endeavoured to remove. I hope at leaſt ſome will lay aſide that envy with which they look upon the Biſhops for the height and dignity of their Office, and <hi>eſteem them very highly in love for their Work ſake;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.13.</note> when they ſhall have ſeen here, that it is not onely an Office of <hi>dignity,</hi> but of <hi>work,</hi> and that work as <hi>good</hi> as the Office is <hi>great.</hi> I will ſay no more to them here, than that the peace and ſafety of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> is ſo bound up with that of the <hi>Church,</hi> that he that is a <hi>friend</hi> to the one, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:115751:3"/>be an <hi>enemy</hi> to the other: And that the Office and Dignity of a Biſhop is ſo <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the peace and ſafety of the Church, that the oppoſing of the <hi>one</hi> muſt needs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get diſorder and confuſion in the <hi>other.</hi> But I will pray, That God, who hath reſtored us to a better Underſtanding of the <hi>Royall</hi> Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Dignity, will likewiſe give us a right Apprehenſion of the <hi>Epiſcopall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 77. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> And as <hi>He led his People like a Flock by the hand of Moſes and Aaron,</hi> ſo He will make us all the people of his paſture, and the Sheep of his hands, and lead us like a Flock in the right and good way, which will make us as happy as we can be in this World, and finally bring us to the perfection of our Happineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:115751:4"/>in his Eternall Kingdome. And herein I doubt not but Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is ready to joyne Your Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with thoſe of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your LORDSHIPS Most humble and moſt faithful Servant, <hi>JOHN SUDBURY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115751:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 TIM. 3.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>This is a true ſaying, If a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Office of a Biſhop, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth a good work.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here needs no other <hi>Preface</hi> or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction to commend <hi>this</hi> ſaying to our attention, then this which the Apoſtle hath ſet before it, <hi>This is a true ſaying.</hi> For ſeeing there is not <hi>any</hi> ſaying in <hi>this</hi> book which is not as true as <hi>this,</hi> we may be <hi>ſure</hi> there is ſome difference between the truth of <hi>this</hi> and <hi>other</hi> ſayings, which made the Apoſtle <hi>ſo particularly</hi> commend it to us. And though it be not eaſie to determine poſitively <hi>what it is,</hi> it is not hard to ſay <hi>what it might be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For firſt, it is eaſie to perceive what great need there was to arm and fence it well againſt the contradiction of ſuch as would oppoſe and <hi>gainſay</hi> it. For there is not <hi>any</hi> ſaying in <hi>this</hi> book which hath met with <hi>more</hi> and <hi>greater</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and contradiction. The Office of a Biſhop hath been the <hi>mark</hi> at which not onely the <hi>profeſs'd Enemies</hi> of the Church have bent <hi>their</hi> bows and ſhot <hi>their</hi> arrows; but likewiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115751:5"/>
               <hi>they</hi> who have the greateſt contention with each other, which of them ſhould be the better, if not the only Chriſtian Church; they on the one ſide contending for one Biſhop over the whole Church, and making all the reſt but his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; the other would have as many Biſhops as there are Miniſters, which is in effect to have none.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, the truth of this ſaying is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a matter of <hi>great</hi> importance, worthy of more then ordinary <hi>regard,</hi> which might move the Apoſtle to commend it to a <hi>more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> attention. For there is not a word in it which will not require and deſerve a diſtinct and particular conſideration. Firſt, here is the Office of a Biſhop; ſecondly, the Work belonging to that Office; thirdly, the Goodneſs of that Work; fourthly, the Deſire of the Office, and of the good Work: the one ſet down by way of ſuppoſition, <hi>If a man deſire the Office of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop;</hi> the other by way of inference or conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereupon, <hi>he deſireth a good work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the particulars in the Text, of which I ſhall ſpeak in the ſame order that I have propoſed them, beginning firſt with the <hi>Office</hi> of a Biſhop.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is here tranſlated <hi>the Office of a Biſhop,</hi> ſignifies not the bare Office or Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Biſhop, as it is an Office of work, but the Office together with the Dignity and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence, the Power and Authority, which is ſo eſſential to it, and ſo neceſſary for the due exerciſe and diſcharge of that Office, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115751:5"/>be without it. As likewiſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies not the bare Office, but the Office together with the Dignity of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. Which Dignity the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> was carefull to aſſert and maintain, as well as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Office. And it is the more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in him, becauſe he was a man ſo far from all manner of arrogance and vain-glory, that no man could have more humble thoughts of himſelf. Inſomuch that when he ſpeaks of himſelf,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.9.</note> he calls himſelf the <hi>least of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> though he knew <hi>he was not inferiour to the chiefeſt Apoſtles;</hi> and not only the leaſt of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, but <hi>leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 3.8.</note> but when he ſpeaks of his Office, he ſaith, <hi>In as much as I am the Apoſtle of the Gentiles,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.13.</note> I magnifie mine Office.</hi> And truly we likewiſe have <hi>great</hi> reaſon to magnifie the Office of a Biſhop, <hi>ſo great,</hi> that St. <hi>Hierom</hi> (who was not partial to the Dignity of that Order) confeſſeth that the <hi>ſafety of the Church</hi> depends upon it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiae ſalus pendet in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate ſummi Sacerdotis; cui ſi non exors quaedam &amp; ab omnibus emine is detu pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas, tot in ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiis efficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſchiſmata quot ſacerdotes.</hi> Hieron. ad Lucif.</note> 
               <hi>The ſafety of the Church</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>depends upon the dignity of the high Prieſt; to whom unleſſe there be given an extraordinary and eminent power, there will be as many Schiſms in the Church as there be Prieſts.</hi> And we have ſeen the truth hereof by ſo ſad experience of late years, that it will be the more ſeaſonable at this time, and eſpecially up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occaſion, to ſpeak ſomething of the Dignity of this Office.</p>
            <p>The word in the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifies properly an <hi>over-ſeeing</hi> or <hi>ſuperintendency;</hi> for a Biſhop is an Overſeer or Superintendent.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115751:6"/>And we know that he that is ſet to overſee, muſt be in a higher ſtation then they are whom he is ſet to overſee. There be many other names and titles by which they are deſcrib'd in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and in the <hi>beſt</hi> Writers of the <hi>ancient</hi> Church, which are names and titles not onely of Office, but likewiſe of <hi>Dignity</hi> and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.10.</note> They are <hi>the Stars in the right hand of Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12.42.</note> the <hi>Angels of the Churches;</hi> the <hi>Stewards</hi> whom the Lord hath ſet over his family; the <hi>Paſtors</hi> or <hi>Sheepherds</hi> of the flock which he hath <hi>purchaſed</hi> with his <hi>own blood;</hi> the <hi>ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles;</hi> the <hi>Vicars of Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>high Prieſts;</hi> the <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of the Church. All theſe are names and titles of no <hi>ſmall</hi> Dignity, and ſome of them likewiſe of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority;</hi> wherein the Office of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> differs from that of a <hi>Prieſt</hi> or Presbyter: not only as <hi>Celſior gradus,</hi> a <hi>higher degree;</hi> the Biſhop among the Prieſts being, as it is ſaid of the high Prieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his brethren,
<note place="margin">Ecclus 50.12.</note> 
               <hi>like the Cedar among the Palm-trees;</hi> but it is likewiſe <hi>poteſtas alterius ordinis,</hi> a <hi>power of another Order,</hi> a <hi>power</hi> to <hi>ordain other Officers</hi> in the Church, and to overſee <hi>them,</hi> that they may do <hi>their</hi> work as they ſhould, or if they will not, to put them <hi>beſide</hi> their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <p>This Power and Authority of the Biſhop was ſo well known to St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> (whom I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rather, becauſe he himſelf was no Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and is thought by ſuch as would have no Biſhops to be a friend to them) I ſay, St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> when <hi>Vigilantius</hi> broach'd his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115751:6"/>wonders that the <hi>Biſhop in whoſe Dioceſe he was a Prieſt did not withſtand his madneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Miror ſanctum Epiſcopum, in cujus parochia eſſe Presbyter dicitur, acquic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcere furori ejus, &amp; non v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rgâ Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>câ virgâ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>â confringere vas inutile, &amp; tradere in int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rnis, ut ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ritus ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus fiat.</hi> S H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eron. Epiſt. ad Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parium. <hi>Et tu quidem honor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fice circa nos &amp; pro ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria hum litate feciſti ut mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les de eò nobis conqueri, cum pro epiſcopatûs vigore &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrae au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate haberes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtatem qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> poſſes de illo ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>m v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>art.</hi> Cypr. Epiſt 65. ad R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum.</note> and break in pieces that unprofitable veſſel, and deliver him up to the destruction of the fleſh, that his ſpirit might be ſaved.</hi> By virtue of the <hi>ſame</hi> power St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> puniſh'd the delinquent Clergy of his Dioceſe, by depriving them of their moneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dividends; and writing to <hi>Rogatianus,</hi> a <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> who had made his complaint to him of a Deacon that behaved himſelf injuriouſly toward him, he tells him, <hi>it was a great humility in him to complain of one over whom he himſelf had Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thority and Power to right himſelf, by virtue of his Epiſcopal Office, and the Authority of his Chair.</hi> And herein likewiſe the Hierarchy of the Church differs from that of the Angels; for though there be degrees among them, ſome are of a higher Order, and others of a lower; yet we do not find that they of the higher Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der have power to depoſe or degrade thoſe of the lower; there is no need of any ſuch power, where all are regular and orderly: but ſuch a power there is in the Hierarchy of the Church, and muſt be, becauſe it cannot be ſuppoſed that men will be ſo orderly as Angels.</p>
            <p>There is therefore a <hi>neceſsity</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Office, with <hi>this</hi> Power and Authority, to preſerve <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and to prevent the <hi>manifold</hi> and <hi>great</hi> miſchiefs which Parity, the Mother of <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> would ſoon produce: which muſt needs be greater in the <hi>Church,</hi> then in the <hi>State.</hi> For there is <hi>nothing</hi> that ſo <hi>effectually</hi> rules the Multitude as <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115751:7"/>the <hi>name</hi> whereof is <hi>ſo</hi> venerable, that they are more apt to follow their <hi>Preachers</hi> then their <hi>Princes;</hi> becauſe they look upon them as the Miniſters of God, whoſe <hi>Office</hi> it is to teach them <hi>his word</hi> and will; and are afraid to think amiſſe of any thing which they hear from <hi>them,</hi> leſt in ſo doing they ſhould ſet themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>God:</hi> whereby it comes to paſſe that there is ſcarce any <hi>Errour</hi> ſo <hi>groſſe</hi> which ſome of them will not <hi>believe,</hi> or any <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> ſo <hi>great</hi> which ſome of them will not practice, and think thereby to do God ſervice, if it be preach'd to them as a matter and duty of <hi>Religion.</hi> And how much this may tend to the diſturbance of the publick Peace and Government, is eaſie to be ſeen. For remedy whereof, if the ſovereign <hi>Prince</hi> interpoſe his power only, he runs the hazard of being reputed an <hi>enemy</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and of <hi>Religion,</hi> then which nothing can be more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to him not only in point of <hi>reputation,</hi> but of <hi>ſafety</hi> likewiſe.</p>
            <p>There is no better Remedy againſt all <hi>this</hi> miſchief, then that <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>good, grave</hi> and <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> men, ſuch as are <hi>able by ſound Doctrine both to exhort and to convince the gain-ſayers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.9.</note> ſhould be ſet up over the reſt, with <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>charge them that they teach no other Doctrine,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> writes to <hi>Timothy,</hi> whom he left at <hi>Epheſus</hi> to this end, 1 Tim. 1.3. <hi>and to ſtop the mouths of ſuch unruly and vain talkers, who ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert whole houſes, teaching things which they ought not,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle writes to <hi>Titus,</hi> whom he left at <hi>Creet</hi> to do this Office, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.10, 11.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115751:7"/>
            <p>This is too great an Office for <hi>one</hi> man to exerciſe over the <hi>whole</hi> Church: as therefore Chriſt choſe not one onely, but twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to whom he committed <hi>this Office</hi> and truſt: ſo his Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">John 20 21.</note> 
               <hi>whom he ſent as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſent him, i.e.</hi> with a power to ſend others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them with the like power, ordained, not one B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhop onely in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> but one in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very City. But as it is too great a power and truſt to be committed to <hi>one</hi> man over the <hi>whole</hi> Church, ſo likewiſe it was not for the good of unity and order that it ſhould be committed unto every one that was fit to bear ſome Office in the Church. As therefore Chriſt, who had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Diſciples,
<note place="margin">John 4.1.</note> that <hi>the Phariſees had heard that he made more Diſciples than</hi> John, did not make them all Apoſtles; and though he gave diverſity of Gifts and Graces to divers men, yet among all theſe he choſe but twelve Apoſtles: ſo the Apoſtles after him ordained Elders or Biſhops, not in <hi>every Village,</hi> but onely in <hi>every City;</hi> making the Government of the Church herein conformable to that of the State, where the Praefect or Governour of a Province or Country had his reſidence in the <hi>City,</hi> but his Juriſdiction in the <hi>Country</hi> round about. And this <hi>conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in the Government of the Church to that of the State was ſo much the better, becauſe <hi>that kind</hi> of Government in the <hi>State</hi> was <hi>beſt</hi> for the State, and the like Government in the <hi>Church</hi> was <hi>beſt</hi> for the Church.</p>
            <p>It were eaſie here to ſhew how all Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſo much the better, as the Power and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115751:8"/>Authority of it is more united in one man; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Piecincts of it be ſo great, that it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the proportion of any one mans ability: That where it is divided, though it be but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two, it is very apt to deſtroy it ſelf. That a Family is beſt ordered, where there is <hi>but one Pater-familias;</hi> a Ship, where there is <hi>but one</hi> Maſter, who commands all the Officers under him; a Caſtle, where there is <hi>but one</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to whom all obey; an Army, where there is <hi>but one</hi> General, that commands all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in their ſeveral charges; a City, where there is one Mayor, though many Aldermen; a Kingdom, where there is <hi>but one</hi> King, though <hi>many</hi> inferiour Magiſtrates. And after this it were as eaſie to ſhew that ſuch an orderly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is as decent and neceſſary in a Church as in any of theſe. It were likewiſe eaſie to ſhew how agreeable <hi>this</hi> order is to <hi>that</hi> which God himſelf eſtabliſhed in the Church of the <hi>Jews;</hi> what a fit reſemblance there is between the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, Prieſts and High-prieſts in the one, and the Deacons, Presbyters and Biſhop in the other; how <hi>careful</hi> Chriſt was to retein in <hi>his</hi> Church, whatſoever he found commendable in <hi>that;</hi> and how wary of introducing any innovation, where there was no neceſſity. And after this I could ſhew you how all Religions have had <hi>their Prieſts</hi> and <hi>their High-prieſts;</hi> the light of natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon teaching them that they muſt have ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that Religion cannot be publickly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed without Prieſts, nor by them ſo well, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they be under ſome High-prieſt; it being
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115751:8"/>neceſſary for the good of <hi>order,</hi> that there be a <hi>ſubordination,</hi> and that to hold <hi>many</hi> together <hi>in one,</hi> they muſt be all <hi>under one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what need all this to juſtifie this order in the Church, of which we ſpeak, when it is a thing ſo clear, that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> calls it <hi>Traditionem Apoſtolicam toti mundo manifeſtam, an Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal tradition manifeſt to all the world;</hi> and writes that <hi>many</hi> of the Biſhops in <hi>his</hi> time could derive their ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles? And the moſt <hi>ancient</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> Writers of the Hiſtory of the Church have left us the names of them in ſome of the <hi>principal</hi> Cities of the <hi>world,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the <hi>time</hi> and <hi>order</hi> of their ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles. There is not a <hi>Council,</hi> not a <hi>Father,</hi> which might not be produc'd as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Truth. Yea, thoſe <hi>Hereticks</hi> who would have <hi>unchurch'd</hi> all the world but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the <hi>Novatians</hi> and the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> had <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> of their own, as thinking them ſo <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the being of a <hi>well-form'd</hi> Church, that to be <hi>without</hi> them were to unchurch themſelves. One ambitious Presbyter there was, <hi>Aerius</hi> by name, who becauſe he could not be a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> would have none; becauſe he could not raiſe himſelf to the <hi>Dignity</hi> of that Office, ſtudied to bring down that Office and levell it with his <hi>own.</hi> But he was condemn'd by the <hi>whole</hi> Church, and remains upon the Catalogue of Hereticks.</p>
            <p>To all theſe Teſtimonies we may adde one which is more than <hi>all</hi> theſe, the teſtimony of <hi>Chriſt</hi> from <hi>heaven,</hi> in an Epiſtle ſent by an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> to his <hi>beloved</hi> Diſciple and Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115751:9"/>bearing witneſs both of the <hi>antiquity</hi> of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and of his <hi>own approbation</hi> of it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi> where interpreting the myſtery of the <hi>ſeven ſtars in his right hand,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>the ſeven ſtars are the Angels of the ſeven Churches.</hi> Where by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches he means the ſeven famous Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which are mentioned afterward, to whom his Epiſtles are directed; and by the ſeven Stars and the ſeven Angels, he muſt mean the ſeven <hi>Biſhops</hi> of thoſe ſeven Churches: for if he had meant ſeven Presbyteries or Claſſes, it had been more proper to have call'd them ſeven Conſtellations than ſeven Stars, and ſeven Quire of Angels than ſeven Angels.</p>
            <p>Other Offices there are in the Church but the Office of a Biſhop is the higheſt, to which all other Offices are as <hi>ſteps</hi> or degrees, according to that which we read in the 13 Verſe of this Chapter, <hi>They who have uſed the Office of a Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con well, purchaſe to themſelves a good degree,</hi> or, as we may render it, a fair <hi>aſcent</hi> or <hi>ſtep, i. e.</hi> to a <hi>higher</hi> degree of Office in the Church. But there is no Office in the Church to which the Office of a Biſhop may be call'd a <hi>ſtep</hi> or <hi>degree.</hi> One Biſhop may have a greater Dioceſe than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, which is not by <hi>Divine,</hi> but Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal right, limiting not the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> but the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of it, for the good of <hi>order,</hi> and to avoyd confuſion: but he that hath the <hi>leaſt</hi> Dioceſe is as <hi>much</hi> a Biſhop as he that hath the greateſt, as he that hath a little Flock is as much a Shepherd as he that hath a greater. Every Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is as much a Biſhop as the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115751:9"/>or as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> for he is a ſucceſſor of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the <hi>whole</hi> Epiſcopal Office, which is all that in which they have or were to have any ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors.</p>
            <p>The differences between an Apoſtle and a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop are onely in ſuch acceſſories as do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Office of a Biſhop, but onely to the Time in which <hi>they</hi> exerciſed that Office. The Apoſtles were eye-witneſſes of Chriſt; which none could be but ſuch as <hi>were converſant with him during the time that he went in and out among them,</hi> unleſs it were by viſion from Heaven,
<note place="margin">Acts 1.21.</note> as St. <hi>Paul.</hi> But as they were <hi>teſtes oculati, eye-witneſſes;</hi> ſo the <hi>Biſhops their ſucceſſors</hi> were and are <hi>teſtes inſtructi,</hi> witneſſes inſtructed and taught. They who were firſt, were indued with <hi>extraordinary</hi> Gifts and Graces of the Spirit of God, which was pour'd forth upon the Church like the holy Oyle upon the <hi>head</hi> of <hi>Aaron:</hi> but the <hi>ſame</hi> Spirit of God which was pour'd forth upon <hi>them,</hi> runs down upon the <hi>Biſhops</hi> their ſucceſſors as <hi>truly,</hi> though not ſo <hi>plentifully.</hi> They had their Calling <hi>immediatly</hi> from Chriſt; the Biſhops their ſucceſſors have their Calling as <hi>truly</hi> from Chriſt, though not ſo <hi>immediatly.</hi> The Apoſtles choſe their ſucceſſors, and they others after them: but they did not <hi>beſtow</hi> that Power and Authority upon them, but were one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Miniſters of God and Chriſt. It was <hi>by</hi> them that the Epiſcopal power was given, but not <hi>from</hi> them, but from him from whom all Powers are ordain'd. And therefore all Biſhops anciently were wont to write themſelves Biſhops
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115751:10"/>of ſuch or ſuch a City: not by the conſtitution of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> or their ſucceſſors, nor by the favour of thoſe who <hi>elected</hi> them to their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; but by the <hi>grace of God.</hi> The Apoſtles were Biſhops of the whole Church; ſo is every Biſhop by Divine right: the limitation of them to ſuch or ſuch a Dioceſe, which is by Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical conſtitution, is not a limitation of their power and authority, but of the exerciſe of it, not to leſſen them, but to preſerve peace and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in the Church. In a word, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were the chief Governours of the Church which was in their time, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the Church in their time. And what need we ſay more for the Dignity of an Office, which is ſo much the <hi>ſame</hi> with that of an Apoſtle?</p>
            <p>But becauſe I have ſaid thus much of it, it is the more needfull, before I paſſe from <hi>this</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, to ſpeak ſomething of the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this Power and Authority, which is the <hi>higheſt</hi> in the Church, and that which is the higheſt in the Kingdoms of the world. <hi>Both</hi> are powers <hi>ordained</hi> of God, not to <hi>oppoſe</hi> or <hi>confront,</hi> but to <hi>aſsiſt</hi> each other. The Power of the one is the power of <hi>his</hi> Sword, which is a <hi>rod of iron;</hi> the Power of the other is the power of <hi>his</hi> Sword, which is the <hi>ſword of the Spirit,</hi> the Word of God. The Power of the one ſerves to puniſh them that will not be ſubject to him with <hi>baniſhment, impriſonment, confiſcation, death,</hi> &amp;c. The Power of the other baniſheth <hi>no</hi> man out of his <hi>Country,</hi> but only out of the <hi>Church;</hi> it cuts off no man from the <hi>land of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115751:10"/>living,</hi> but only from the <hi>communion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> it deprives no man of <hi>any</hi> right that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to him either as a <hi>man,</hi> or as a member of any <hi>Common-wealth, Kingdom</hi> or other Society in them, but only that which belongs to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. In which it deprives him of nothing, but that to which he hath no right.</p>
            <p>And as the Powers are diſtinct, ſo likewiſe are the Ends of them: the End of the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>civill</hi> and <hi>temporall good</hi> of them that are under it; the End of the other, the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>eternall</hi> good.</p>
            <p>But theſe two diſtinct Powers with their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Ends do not <hi>hinder</hi> but <hi>help</hi> each other. For while the Biſhop uſeth <hi>his</hi> power to make men good <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> he makes them ſo much the better <hi>Subjects;</hi> it being a part of their <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to be <hi>good Subjects,</hi> their <hi>Allegiance</hi> is bound up in their <hi>Religion,</hi> ſo as they cannot <hi>depart</hi> from the <hi>one</hi> unleſſe they likewiſe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce</hi> the <hi>other;</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> cannot be a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> but he muſt depart from his <hi>Faith</hi> and turn <hi>infidel,</hi> if not in <hi>word,</hi> yet in <hi>deed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Spirituall Sword doth not <hi>claſh</hi> with the Temporall, but joyn with it in the ſame work, and ſo aſſiſts and ſtrengthens it, as that it doth that work which belongs properly to the temporall Sword better than it ſelf. The King with his Sword commands all that are under him to live in obedience to <hi>him</hi> and to his Lawes, for fear of incurring <hi>his</hi> diſpleaſure, and falling under <hi>his</hi> power, which can but kill the Body. The Biſhop with <hi>his</hi> power com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115751:11"/>ſubjects to be obedient to their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns and their Lawes, out of Conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, whoſe Miniſters they are, for fear of <hi>his</hi> diſpleaſure, and falling under his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who can caſt both Soul and Body into hell.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Spirituall</hi> Sword doth not claſh with the <hi>Temporall,</hi> ſo neither doth the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall</hi> Sword claſh with the <hi>Spirituall;</hi> as I could ſhew you, but that I muſt remember that my Text ſpeaks not of the Office of a King, but of a Biſhop, and there be other particulars in it for which I muſt reſerve ſome time: and therefore I paſſe on to the next Particular, which is the <hi>Work</hi> belonging to this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <p>The Office of a Biſhop is an Office <hi>not</hi> of <hi>Dignity only,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but of <hi>Work:</hi> the Dignity is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd to it for the <hi>Works</hi> ſake, partly as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the <hi>better</hi> exerciſe and diſcharge of it, and partly as a due for the <hi>worthineſs</hi> of the Work. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>We beſeech you, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to know them that labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you; and to eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake.</hi> He doth not ſay for their <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> but for their <hi>Works</hi> ſake. For the <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> were not made for the Biſhop, that he might have an <hi>Office,</hi> but the <hi>Biſhop</hi> was made for the <hi>Office,</hi> and the <hi>Office</hi> for the <hi>Work.</hi> This is the end of all the Offices which Chriſt hath ſet in the Church. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. <hi>He gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Paſtors and Doctors, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115751:11"/>work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt;</hi> Not for the dignity of a Magiſtracy, but <hi>for the work of the Miniſtry;</hi> for every one of theſe Offices is a miniſtry, even the higheſt of them all. For <hi>who is Paul? and who is Apollo?
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.5.</note> but ministers?</hi> and a miniſtry is a <hi>Work.</hi> As therefore in the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Prieſts, not that they might have the <hi>Office</hi> of Prieſthood, but <hi>that: they might mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to the Lord in the Prieſts Office:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 7.35.</note> So in the Chriſtian Church he hath ordained <hi>ſeverall Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> but <hi>all</hi> of them to <hi>this</hi> end, that every one of them might <hi>miniſter</hi> to him in his <hi>Office.</hi> When our Saviour committed <hi>this</hi> Office to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he did not ſay to him, <hi>Be thou a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> or a <hi>Paſtor;</hi> but he ſaid unto him, <hi>Feed my ſheep,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 21.15.</note> to mind him chiefly of his <hi>Work</hi> for which he put him in Office. And S. <hi>Peter</hi> in like manner minds the Elders or Biſhops, not to ſtand ſo much upon their Dignity, as to look well to their <hi>Work.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1, <hi>&amp;c. The Elders which are among you I exhort, who am alſo an Elder—Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof—not as being lords over God's heritage,</hi> &amp;c. For they are not the lords,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.42.</note> 
               <hi>but the Stewards, whom the Lord hath ſet over his houſhold;</hi> not to exerciſe dominion, like the Princes of the Gentiles, <hi>but to give them their portion of meat in due ſeaſon.</hi> It is not <hi>their</hi> flock, but the flock of <hi>God,</hi> over which they are ſet; not to feed <hi>themſelves</hi> with the fat, and to cloth <hi>themſelves</hi> with the wooll, but to feed and overſee the <hi>flock</hi> of God: it is not <hi>their</hi> heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115751:12"/>but the heritage of <hi>God</hi> which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them; not as a principality, to have a <hi>dominion</hi> in it, but as a <hi>charge,</hi> to have the <hi>care</hi> and <hi>inſpection</hi> over it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Work</hi> which belongs to the Office of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> muſt needs be greater then that which belongs to the Office of a <hi>Priest</hi> or Presbyter: for every <hi>Biſhop</hi> is a Prieſt, but every Prieſt is not a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> as much greater as the Office is higher, and the ſphere in which his work lies of a larger compaſſe. A Prieſt or Presbyter is over <hi>his</hi> flock, inaſmuch as it is his Office to miniſter to them the things that are holy, and to inſtruct and teach them the word of God: but <hi>his</hi> flock is but a ſmall part of that <hi>greater</hi> flock which the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is to overſee, and it is his <hi>work</hi> to <hi>overſee</hi> not the <hi>flock</hi> only, but the <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers</hi> of the ſeveral parts of his flock; for though they be over their ſeverall flocks, they are <hi>all</hi> under <hi>him.</hi> It is his work to overſee the whole buſineſs of the Church; to ſee that the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God be duly and decently celebrated; that all the Congregations be ſupplyed with ſuch, and ſuch only, as <hi>teach the things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſound Doctrine that cannot be condemned;</hi> that in their life and converſation they behave themſelves in all things as the Miniſters of God, <hi>giving no offence in any thing, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry be not blam'd;</hi> that ſuch as are ſcandalous be <hi>remov'd,</hi> if they will not be <hi>reform'd;</hi> to <hi>purge</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of them, if they will not <hi>purge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</hi> to ſee that they whom they have bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizd be firſt inſtructed by them, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by him.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115751:12"/>
            <p>Some indeed there are, who think the work of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is nothing but to <hi>preach;</hi> and if he ſhould preach ſo often as they would have him, he ſhould have work enough of that. I do not deny, but that this is a part of his work, a work which belongs to him as he is a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> ſo properly, that it belongs to no other Officer in the Church but by Commiſſion from him.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Age of the Church, while the Apoſtles retained the Office of a Biſhop to themſelves, there was little other work but that of Preaching; and ſo much of that as was enough to take up all their time. The great work of their time was to gather together the Sheep that were ſcatter'd abroad, and bring them into the <hi>fold</hi> of the Church, to convert Infidels to the faith, of which they had not heard, and of which they could not <hi>hear without a Preacher.</hi> And becauſe this was a great Work, to the end they might give the more atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to it, they committed ſome other parts of their work to others, that could do that as well as themſelves. It was a part of their work to <hi>baptize,</hi> for Chriſt ſent them not only to <hi>teach</hi> all nations, but likewiſe to <hi>baptize</hi> them: but when it was too <hi>great</hi> a work for them to do both, they committed the work of <hi>baptizing</hi> to their Diſciples, giving themſelves to the work of <hi>Preaching,</hi> the <hi>leſs</hi> work giving way to the <hi>greater.</hi> So likewiſe it was a part of <hi>their</hi> work to take <hi>care</hi> of the poor: but when it came to be a <hi>great</hi> Work, by reaſon of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115751:13"/>great number of them, and the complaint of ſome that they were neglected, they inſtituted the <hi>Office of Deacons, whom they ſet over that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs,
<note place="margin">Acts 6.4.</note> giving themſelves to Prayer and to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Work of the Biſhops their Succeſſors, was, not ſo much to convert Infidels, as to confute Hereticks and Schiſmaticks; not ſo much to gather the Sheep into the fold, as to keep them from going aſtray, and to keep the Wolves from entring in among them. To which end they have other work beſide that of Preaching, and for which reaſon the Apoſtle in this Chapter tells us, that a Biſhop muſt not only <hi>be apt to teach,</hi> but he <hi>muſt be one that knows how to Rule his own houſe well:</hi> and he gives this reaſon for it. <hi>For if a man know not how to Rule his own houſe, how ſhall he take care of the Church of God?</hi> Where it is evident that it is the Work of a Biſhop to take care of the Church of God.</p>
            <p>This is a Work that may take up ſo much of his time, and require ſo much of his paines, as will diſable him from the frequency of Preaching, eſpecially when through age and the infirmities incident thereunto, he muſt either do it with great diſadvantages, or omit ſome other part of his work, which is <hi>no leſs,</hi> if not <hi>more</hi> neceſſary then this. For it is not with the Preaching of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> as it was with that of an <hi>Apoſtle:</hi> the <hi>Apostles</hi> preach'd as they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd by the Holy Ghoſt; the <hi>Biſhop</hi> muſt <hi>give diligence to reading, hearing, meditation.</hi> He muſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115751:13"/>
               <hi>ſtudy to approve himſelf to God,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2, 15.</note> a workman that needeth not to be aſham'd, rightly dividing the word of truth.</hi> This is a work that cannot be done without much <hi>ſtudy.</hi> But all this work muſt not lie upon the Biſhop only; there be other Officers under him who have <hi>partem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitudinis, part of the care,</hi> though not <hi>plenitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem poteſtatis, the fulneſs of the power:</hi> and theſe having not ſo much of the work of Ruling, may ſpend the more of their time in Preaching. But ſtill it is the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Work, to ſee that they, to whom he commits this part of his Work, be ſuch as the Apoſtle adviſeth <hi>Timothy</hi> to make choice of, <hi>faithfull men,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2.</note> ſuch as ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</hi> Wherein there is great care and circumſpection to be had, as we may ſee by the ſtrict charge which he gives him concerning it. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. <hi>I charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the elect Angels, that thou obſerve theſe things, without preferring one before another. Do nothing through partiality; lay hands ſuddenly on no man, neither be thou par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of other mens ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet this is not all his Work. He muſt not only take heed to <hi>whom</hi> he commits this Work, but likewiſe ſee that <hi>none but ſuch</hi> as are <hi>ſent</hi> to the work take it upon them, and that they who are ſent, do the work for which they are ſent, and not through <hi>ignorance</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign miſtake their errand, and teach things which they ought not. For when Chriſt commends the Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus for examining them who ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.2.</note> he doth imply
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115751:14"/>that this was a part of <hi>his</hi> Work, and tacitly blame thoſe who having the <hi>ſame</hi> Office, have not the <hi>ſame</hi> Care. And this is likewiſe a great Work. For if in the Apoſtles time there were, as he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>many unruly and vain talkers, whoſe mouths muſt be ſtop'd;</hi> it is not like but there would be <hi>many</hi> ſuch afterward.
<note place="margin">Act. 20 29, 30.</note> 
               <hi>He knew that after his departure grievous wolves would enter in, not ſparing the flock; and that among themſelves would men ariſe ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them.</hi> And we know that Popularity was not the ſin of that Age and place only: we find the like complaint in the Church of <hi>Galatia;</hi> there were falſe Teachers crept in among them, who <hi>withdrew them from him that had call'd them in the grace of Chriſt, unto another Goſpel,</hi> Gal 1.6. and chap. 4 17. he tells us who and what manner of men they were. <hi>They zealouſly affect you, but not well; yea they would exclude us, that you might affect them:</hi> i. e. they make profeſſion of a zealous affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the good of the people to whom they preach, but their aim is to ſteal away their hearts and affections from all other men to themſelves; in purſuance of which deſign, they would preach <hi>down</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to preach <hi>up themſelves.</hi> And what wonder to ſee a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular affection tranſport men to preach down Biſhops, when the ſame affection ſo early tranſported ſome to preach down Apoſtles?</p>
            <p>But it is not only the Popularity and Pride of ſuch <hi>Teachers,</hi> but likewiſe a <hi>giddineſſe</hi> in the <hi>people,</hi> which makes more work yet for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115751:14"/>the <hi>Biſhop.</hi> The Apoſtle foreſaw it, and gave early notice of it to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. <hi>The time will come that they will not endure ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but according to their own luſts they will heap up to themſelves Teachers, having itching ears.</hi> And this muſt needs make more work for the Biſhop, for the more greedy they are in heaping up ſuch Teachers, the more vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant and carefull muſt he be to pull them down.</p>
            <p>In a word, there is Work enough in the Church for the Biſhop, and for all other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers under him, wherein his care muſt be to mind <hi>that</hi> Work or ſervice <hi>moſt,</hi> by which he may <hi>moſt</hi> promote the <hi>Glory</hi> of God and the <hi>Good</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> and to ſee that they to whom he commits the reſt of the work, <hi>doe</hi> their work as they <hi>ought</hi> to do it. And ſo much for the Second Particular, in theſe words, the <hi>work</hi> which belongs to the Office of a Biſhop. I come now to the third Particular, which is the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of the Work.</p>
            <p>It is very well rendred in our Tranſlation a <hi>good work,</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin">The good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that work.</note> not an <hi>honest</hi> or a <hi>pious</hi> or an <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> work, as it might be rendred: not but that it is all theſe, but becauſe it is all theſe and all theſe are comprehended in this expreſſion of a good work.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is an <hi>honourable</hi> work; for it is the work in which they are call'd <hi>workers together with God.</hi> And that for very good reaſon: for that, which our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.17. <hi>my Father. worketh hitherto, and I work,</hi> is as true now, as it was then when he ſpake it, and that more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115751:15"/>in <hi>this</hi> then in any <hi>other</hi> work. For there is nothing on earth <hi>ſo dear</hi> to God as his <hi>Church;</hi> nothing to which his <hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> extends <hi>more</hi> then to the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>orderly</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of it. It is the work for which he ſent his Sonne from heaven; no other name or title doth ſo well expreſs the work for which he came into the world, as that of the <hi>great Shepherd and Biſhop of our ſouls.</hi> For which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon diverſe of the ancient Fathers, by the loſt ſheep in the Parable underſtand Mankind in the ſtate of his Fall; by the <hi>ninety and nine</hi> that went not aſtray, the <hi>Angels</hi> that kept their firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; by the man that left the ninety and nine, to ſeek the ſheep that was loſt, the <hi>man Chriſt Jeſus</hi> that came <hi>down</hi> from Heaven the <hi>habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Angels,</hi> to ſeek and ſave <hi>man</hi> that was loſt. It is the work for which he ſent abroad his Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">John 20.21.</note> 
               <hi>as his Father ſent him.</hi> The work for which he ſent down his Spirit upon them ſoon after his return to heaven, and his exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the right hand of God: The work for which he hath promis'd to be with them and with their Succeſſors unto the end of the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. ult. And this is ſufficient to ſhew how <hi>honourable</hi> a work it is.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe as <hi>pious, honeſt</hi> and <hi>Charitable</hi> a work as it is <hi>honourable.</hi> It is the moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable work or ſervice that men can do to God.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>We are unto God a ſweet ſavour of Chriſt,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, ſpeaking of <hi>this</hi> work, which is the work of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> as well as an <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> to ſignify, that as a ſweet and fragrant odour is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115751:15"/>gratefull unto <hi>us,</hi> ſo is <hi>this</hi> work noe leſs accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it is ſo acceptable to God, ſo it is no leſſe for the good and benefit of men. The good which it works moſt <hi>Directly</hi> and <hi>properly</hi> is the <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>eternal</hi> good, which is ſo much better then all that is but <hi>temporall,</hi> that there is <hi>no</hi> compariſon between them. But it is not <hi>ſo particularly</hi> for the ſpirituall and eternall good, but that it is likewiſe <hi>very much</hi> for the temporall. The Hiſtories of all Ages ſince the beginning of Chriſtianity bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>abundantly</hi> of the <hi>manifold</hi> and great <hi>good</hi> which hath been wrought in the world by <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> doing <hi>that</hi> work which belongs to their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. They have been, and are the chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters under God of upholding,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.1.</note> and preſerving <hi>that</hi> Truth which the Apoſtle calls <hi>the truth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Godlineſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> that Godlineſſe of which he ſaith that it <hi>is profitable for all things, having the promiſe of the life which now is, and of that which is to come.</hi> And to the End we might the better conſider how true this is, he adds in the next verſe, <hi>This is a true ſaying and worthy of all acceptation.</hi> And to ſay nothing of the life which is to come, of which no truth ever had ſo clear and ample promiſes there is nothing more profitable for the life which now is. Nothing ſo effectual to reſtrain all the iniquitie which makes one man a Devil to another, or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote <hi>all</hi> that Vertue and Goodneſſe which makes one man a <hi>God</hi> to another. For every iniquity is then moſt carefully avoyded, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115751:16"/>very good work moſt ſincerely and exactly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, when he that avoyds the one and does the other is mov'd thereunto by a <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>Religion.</hi> This is the great advantage which Religion hath above all the beſt Lawes that the wiſdome of men can make, or their juſtice put in execution. The beſt humane Lawes can but lop off the <hi>branches</hi> of thoſe iniquities which <hi>Religion</hi> plucks up by the roots. The power of the <hi>one</hi> is only upon the <hi>Actions</hi> of men, ſo farr forth as they fall under the <hi>cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance</hi> of other men; the power of the <hi>other</hi> upon the <hi>Affections.</hi> It is much if the one can reſtrain men from being <hi>very wicked;</hi> the other hath a power to make them <hi>very good</hi> men.</p>
            <p>And there is no Religion ſo effectuall to take away all manner of Iniquity, and to plant and cheriſh all manner of Vertue as the Chriſtian; the Precepts whereof, which are in their <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> the moſt <hi>pure,</hi> are likewiſe in the <hi>extent</hi> of them the moſt <hi>perfect</hi> and <hi>complete,</hi> reaching to all ſorts of men, in all manner of converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to <hi>Princes, Subjects, Parents, Children, Husbands, Wives, Masters, Servants, Neighbours, Strangers,</hi> to make them <hi>all good</hi> in their <hi>ſeverall</hi> relations, and the better they are, the more happy in each other. The Promiſes annex'd to the obſervation of theſe Precepts are the moſt <hi>high</hi> and <hi>heavenly;</hi> the <hi>confirmation</hi> of thoſe Promiſes the moſt <hi>divine:</hi> to the end that the Promiſes being <hi>ſo</hi> confirm'd might be the more <hi>stedfaſtly believed;</hi> and the <hi>Promiſes</hi> being <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved,</hi> the <hi>Precepts</hi> might be the better <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved;</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115751:16"/>and the Precepts being ſo <hi>obſerv'd,</hi> all men might conſpire together mutually to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the happineſſe of each other, then which they can do nothing better to advance their own. This is the naturall effect of that Truth which is according to Godlineſſe, the receiving and obſerving whereof is the moſt excellent means to procure the favour of God, then which nothing can make the happineſſe of men even in this world more complete.</p>
            <p>Now as all this good comes to men by Chriſtian Religion, ſo the Office and Work of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is of <hi>great</hi> neceſſity and virtue to uphold and <hi>preſerve</hi> this Religion in the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>purity</hi> of it. All other Offices which God hath ſet in the Church, have their work herein, when they are <hi>well</hi> and <hi>duly</hi> performed; but it is the work of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> to ſee that they <hi>be</hi> duly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd. There is no Office ſo <hi>neceſſary</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Schiſms and Factions, then which there is nothing more deſtructive of the <hi>civil</hi> Peace; nothing more fruitful in <hi>all</hi> the <hi>miſchiefs</hi> which make the life of men the moſt unhappy. For what greater miſchiefs among men, then thoſe which ariſe from <hi>hatred, variance, emulation, wrath, ſtrife, ſedition, hereſies, envyings,</hi> &amp;c. and whence ariſe ſo much of theſe, as from the <hi>rents</hi> and <hi>diviſions</hi> in the Church? and whence come theſe <hi>rents</hi> and <hi>diviſions</hi> in the Church, but from the <hi>contempt</hi> which is pour'd forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Office of a Biſhop? <hi>Whence have Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Schiſms ariſen, and do ſtill ariſe, but from this, that the Biſhop, who is one, and is over
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115751:17"/>the Church,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Unde ſchiſmata &amp; haereſes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ortae ſunt, &amp; oriuntur, niſi dum Epiſcopus, qui unus eſt, &amp; Eccleſiae praeeſt, ſuperbâ quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnitur?</hi> Cyprian.</note> is by the Pride and preſumption of ſome deſpis'd?</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian.</hi> This is that which, hath ſo often chang'd the Pulpit into a Theatre, from whence ſo many inſtead of preaching the Goſpel of Peace have blown the Trumpet of War, and perverted that which God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd to turn <hi>ſwords</hi> into <hi>mattocks,</hi> and <hi>ſpeares</hi> into <hi>plowſhares,</hi> to ſerve as the greateſt means of turning <hi>mattocks</hi> into <hi>ſwords,</hi> and <hi>plowſhares</hi> into <hi>ſpeares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, there is nothing ſo neceſſary and effectuall to the happineſſe of men in this life, as to live together in Unity.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, how good and how pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell toget her in unity.</hi> There is no Unity among men ſo ſtrong and ſo good as that, of which Religion is the bond; nothing ſo neceſſary to preſerve the unity of Religion, as the Dignity and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Office of a Biſhop. Brethren will be apt to fall out among themſelves; though they be of one houſe, they will not be of one mind. But as the beſt means to keep or make them friends, is, the reverence which both of them owe to their common Father: ſo the beſt means under God to keep up amity in the Church, or to recover it when it is loſt, is to remember the reverence which all the true Sons of the Church owe to thoſe who are their Fathers in God. And, ſo much for the third Particular in the Text, which is the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of the <hi>work.</hi> I come now to the fourth and laſt, which is the <hi>Deſire</hi> of the <hi>Office,</hi> and of the <hi>good work.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115751:17"/>
            <p>Here are two things to which the word <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> is apply'd, <hi>deſire</hi> the Office,
<note n="4" place="margin">The Deſire of the Office.</note> and <hi>deſire</hi> the good Work: but not in the ſame manner, for the former is by way of Suppoſition only, <hi>If</hi> a man deſire the Office of a Biſhop; the later is by way of Inference or concluſion upon that Suppoſition, <hi>he deſireth a good work.</hi> And though in our Tranſlation it be one and the ſame word in both places, <hi>deſire</hi> the Office and <hi>deſire</hi> the good Work; yet in the originall, there be two different words. The former is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the later is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two words is ſo nice, that our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage cannot well furniſh us with words fit to expreſſe it: but in that there is ſome difference in the Originall, it may teach us, that it is not alwaies one and the ſame <hi>deſire</hi> that is ſet upon the Office, and that which is ſet upon the good Work.</p>
            <p>True it is, that when the Apoſtle wrote this, there was <hi>nothing</hi> in the Office, for which a man would have deſir'd it, but the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of the work. There were no Temporalties annex'd to it, no <hi>Dignity</hi> in the eye of the world, but <hi>ſo much</hi> Work, and that ſo <hi>full</hi> of <hi>perill,</hi> as well as <hi>paines</hi> and <hi>labour,</hi> that had it not been for ſome <hi>great Goodneſſe</hi> in the Work, no man would have undertaken, much leſſe <hi>deſir'd</hi> it. We read of one <hi>Marcus,</hi> who cut off his thumb becauſe he would not be made a Biſhop; and we read of many, who had their heads cut off becauſe they were. But when it came to be an Office, which might
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115751:18"/>be enjoyed not only with Safety, but likewiſe with great Honour and Dignity, and Revenue ſufficient to maintain and uphold that Honour; we read of ſome who have deſir'd the Office of a Biſhop, not for the Goodneſſe of the work, but for the <hi>uppermoſt rooms at feaſts,</hi> and <hi>the higheſt ſeats in the Synagogue,</hi> and <hi>to be call'd of men Rabbi.</hi> Then an Infidel would be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, if he might be a Biſhop, as he that ſaid, <hi>Make me Biſhop of</hi> Rome,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Facite me Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificem Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp; proti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ero Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus.</hi> Praetextat.</note> 
               <hi>and I will ſoon be a Chriſtian.</hi> Thus to deſire the Office of a Biſhop is ſo <hi>far</hi> from being a <hi>good</hi> Work, that the <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> Work it is which belongs to the Office, the <hi>worſe</hi> it is ſo to <hi>deſire</hi> the Office. It is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter queſtion whether it be lawful to <hi>deſire</hi> the Office for the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of the work: for though it be a commendable thing to deſire a <hi>good work,</hi> yet when that good Work is ſo annex'd to a <hi>great</hi> Office, that a man cannot <hi>do the Work</hi> unleſſe he <hi>have the Office,</hi> it may be <hi>ſuſpected</hi> that he looks more upon the <hi>greatneſſe of the Office</hi> then upon the <hi>goodneſſe of the Work;</hi> and <hi>this</hi> Office <hi>requires</hi> a man that is not onely without <hi>blame,</hi> but likewiſe without <hi>ſuſpicion.</hi> I anſwer, generally, it is more ſeemly for a man to <hi>ſtay</hi> till he <hi>be deſir'd</hi> to take the Office than to deſire it before; and it is not unlike but that one that doth <hi>leaſt</hi> deſire the Office, will beſt perform the Work. But yet I will not ſay but that a worthy and good man may have ſo <hi>true</hi> and ſo <hi>great</hi> a deſire to do ſo <hi>good</hi> a Work, as to deſire the <hi>Office</hi> and the <hi>Dignity,</hi> not <hi>for</hi> the Office or the Dignity, but for the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115751:18"/>
               <hi>neceſsity</hi> of <hi>both</hi> to make him <hi>capable</hi> of doing ſo good a Work, and be the worthier and better man for having that deſire.</p>
            <p>But admitting it to be <hi>lawfull,</hi> it may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother queſtion whether it be <hi>prudent.</hi> For I find it a queſtion among Philoſophers, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the part of a <hi>wiſe</hi> man to take upon him a <hi>great</hi> Office; which might well be a queſtion among them, who thought it <hi>ſo great</hi> a happineſſe to be at <hi>quiet</hi> without any trouble to moleſt, and to live at <hi>eaſe</hi> without any bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to oppreſſe, that there could be nothing in the <hi>greateſt</hi> Office to recompenſe the loſſe of this <hi>tranquillity</hi> and <hi>liberty,</hi> which men in great office cannot hope to enjoy: for how can a man be at <hi>quiet</hi> that puts himſelf into the <hi>noyſe</hi> of buſineſs? or how can he live at his <hi>eaſe,</hi> that hath the Government upon his <hi>ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders?</hi> Beſides it is a very deſirable thing to have the thoughts <hi>free</hi> for <hi>Contemplation,</hi> wherein a man may converſe with many of the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> men that have ever been in the world, <hi>who being dead yet ſpeak,</hi> or with Saints and Angels, yea with Chriſt, and God, and any thing, to which his thoughts may have recourſe when they are free: and if there be a life on <hi>earth</hi> that comes near to that of Saints in <hi>Heaven,</hi> it may ſeem to be <hi>this.</hi> But a great Office hath ever too much <hi>work</hi> to allow a man this <hi>freedom</hi> for his thoughts. <hi>Solitude</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> are much fitter for ſuch a purpoſe then the <hi>noyſe</hi> and <hi>croud,</hi> which muſt needs be where there is ſo much Work.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115751:19"/>
            <p>Yet the Philoſopher could think and ſay, that though the <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>ſplendor</hi> of a great Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was no recompenſe for the loſſe of his <hi>quiet</hi> and his <hi>eaſe,</hi> and the <hi>freedom</hi> of his thoughts for contemplation, yet becauſe ſome men <hi>muſt</hi> be in office, it might ſtand with his wiſdome to take it upon him, rather then to ſuffer it to fall into the hands of a <hi>foole:</hi> But ſtill this is but to take the Office upon him, not to <hi>deſire</hi> it. If there be any thing that can make a wiſe and good man deſire this Office, it muſt be the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of the work; there is nothing elſe that can make ſatisfaction for the <hi>great</hi> care and paines which lies <hi>ſo heavy</hi> upon the Office. A <hi>Biſhop</hi> in his Office is like a Candle upon a Candleſtick, ſet up to give <hi>light</hi> to them that are in the houſe, by <hi>conſuming himſelf.</hi> It is but a ſmall recompenſe for <hi>conſuming himſelf,</hi> that he is ſet up in a <hi>golden Candleſtick:</hi> but to give light to them that are in the houſe is ſo good a Work, that for the doing of that a great charity might make a man deſire it, though it be with the diſadvantage to <hi>himſelf,</hi> of conſuming himſelf. I ſay a <hi>great</hi> Charity: for it muſt be a greater Charity then hath been taugh in the School of Philoſophy; but not greater then may be learned in the School of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where we are taught to mind the good of <hi>other men</hi> as well as our own, and a <hi>much greater</hi> good of other men with the loſſe of a leſſe good of our own; according to the pattern and example of our Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter who emptied himſelf that he might fill
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115751:19"/>
               <hi>us.</hi> The <hi>good</hi> of other men, which is or may be wrought by this Work, is ſo <hi>great</hi> as may well invite a good proficient in this Schoole to part with all that is <hi>dear</hi> to him in this world for the procuring of it, though they for whoſe good he conſumes himſelf, return him nothing but <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>good,</hi> and hatred for his good will, according to that which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of himſelf, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15. <hi>I will very gladly ſpend and be ſpent for your ſake, though the more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly I love, the leſſe I be loved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet I do not ſay that <hi>any</hi> man may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Office of a Biſhop for the goodneſs of the Work. For as it is a <hi>good,</hi> ſo it is a <hi>great</hi> work; and as it is <hi>deſirable</hi> becauſe it is <hi>good,</hi> ſo it is no leſſe <hi>dreadfull</hi> becauſe it is <hi>great.</hi> It is a good work to <hi>watch</hi> for the <hi>Souls</hi> of men; but it is a great work,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> ſo to <hi>watch for the ſouls of men, as they that muſt give an account.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Onus Angelicis humeris formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandum.</note> This hath made ſome wiſe and good men to call it a burthen, which the Angels might be afraid to take upon their ſhoulders.
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.16.</note> It made the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to ſay, <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> And if it put ſo great an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> to make that queſtion, he that would offer himſelf in anſwer, had need firſt conſider himſelf, and in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration lay aſide himſelf; or elſe he may eaſily be deceiv'd in himſelf, by thinking too well of his own Sincerity and Sufficiency, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is his own.</p>
            <p>When our Saviour put that queſtion, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42. <hi>Who is that faithfull and wiſe Steward whom the Lord ſhall make Ruler over his houſhold?</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115751:20"/>he is thought by ſome to make enquiry after one that is fitly qualified for the Office of a Biſhop. Certain it is, that ſuch a man ought to be a <hi>wiſe</hi> and a <hi>good</hi> man. For if he be not a <hi>wiſe</hi> man, he will not <hi>know</hi> how to behave himſelf in the <hi>houſe of God:</hi> and if he be not a <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>good</hi> man, he will not <hi>do</hi> that which he <hi>knows</hi> he ought to do. He muſt be a <hi>wiſe</hi> man, that he may <hi>underſtand</hi> his work; and he muſt be a <hi>good</hi> man, that he may <hi>do</hi> it.</p>
            <p>But it may be a queſtion, whether it be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that he be a wiſe and a good man, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Office of a Biſhop do not require the wiſeſt and the beſt of men. When the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith in the following verſes, that he muſt not be a <hi>novice,</hi> and that he muſt be <hi>apt to teach,</hi> and that he muſt be one that <hi>knows how to Rule his own houſe well;</hi> he doth not ſpeak as if one that were thus qualified were wiſe enough, but one that is not thus qualifi'd is <hi>not</hi> wiſe enough. He muſt not only not be a novice, but one that is able <hi>in Doctrine to ſhew uncorruptneſs,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.7, 8.</note> gravity, ſincerity, ſound ſpeech, that cannot be condemn'd, that he that is of the contrary part may be aſham'd,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.9.</note> having no evill to ſay of him.</hi> He muſt not only be apt to teach, but likewiſe able by <hi>ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine both to exhort and to convince the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers.</hi> He muſt not only know how to rule his own houſe well, but likewiſe to take care of the Church of God.</p>
            <p>The Philoſopher, who ſaid that Kingdomes would then be moſt happy when <hi>Kings</hi> were <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> or <hi>Philoſophers</hi> were <hi>Kings,</hi> gave
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115751:20"/>this reaſon for it, That Philoſophers above <hi>all</hi> other men ſpend <hi>their</hi> time and paines in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and conſidering how <hi>God</hi> governs the world: and having this <hi>pattern</hi> ſo much in their eye, they muſt needs be ſo much the fitter to govern under him. The Office of a Biſhop is to govern the Church as a Vicar of Chriſt, and to the end he may do his work well, he had need be one that hath not only well ſtudied his pattern; but ſuch a one as is very conformable thereunto. He muſt have much of his wiſdom, and much of his temper: ſo much of his <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> who <hi>would not break a bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking flax,</hi> as to know how and whom and when he muſt <hi>inſtruct in meekneſs;</hi> and yet ſo much of his <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>zeal,</hi> who whip'd the buyers and ſellers out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as not to be afraid to rebuke ſharply, where it is neceſſary or expedient. He muſt know not only whom to <hi>bind,</hi> but likewiſe whom to <hi>looſe;</hi> leſt while he either binds where he ſhould looſe, or looſes where he ſhould bind, he binds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo much as none can looſe him. He that deſires the Office of a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> had need be wiſer then they who are of his flock: he that deſires the Office of a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> had need be ſo much <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> as he is <hi>higher</hi> then a Prieſt. And not only ſo much <hi>wiſer,</hi> but likewiſe ſo much <hi>better.</hi> There be many good qualities which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle requires in him, in the words which follow theſe of my Text. <hi>A Biſhop muſt be blameleſſe, the husband of one wife, vigilant, ſober, of good behaviour, given to hoſpitality, apt to teach, not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115751:21"/>given to wine, no ſtriker, not greedy of filthy lucre, but patient, not a brauler, not covetous, one that ruleth his own houſe well, not a novice; and moreover he muſt have a good report of them that are without.</hi> But when he ſaith, he muſt <hi>in all things ſhew himſelf a pattern of good workes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.7. 1 Pet. 5.</note> and when St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>he muſt be an example to the flock;</hi> they both imply, that he muſt not only have all theſe good qualities, but theſe and all other good qualities in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and perfection:
<note place="margin">—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Naz. Orat.</hi> 1.</note> for ſo it becomes him that is to ſhew himſelf a pattern and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>When our Saviour conferr'd this Office up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Peter,</hi> he firſt put this queſtion to him,
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Joh. 21.15. 1 Cor. 16.22.</note> 
               <hi>Simon, loveſt thou me more then theſe?</hi> Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Simon lovest thou me?</hi> for he that loves not him, is ſo unworthy to be a Biſhop, that he is not fit to be in the rank of Chriſtians. <hi>If any many love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be anathema maranatha.</hi> But, <hi>Simon, loveſt thou me more then theſe?</hi> to ſhew that he would not have the flock, which he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed with his own blood, committed to any but ſuch as have a ſingular and extraordinary love and devotion to him.</p>
            <p>And thus I have gone through the Particulars in my Text. I ſhall now only look back up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it with two reflections, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>The firſt is with Sadneſſe upon them that look with an evil eye upon this Office, or at leaſt upon the Dignity of it. For the better work it is that belongs to the Office, the worſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115751:21"/>it is, to wiſh there were no ſuch Office, or no ſuch Dignity and Authority, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the better performance of that work which belongs to the Office. There is not an expreſſion of greater miſery that can befall a people, then that which is frequent in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, of <hi>being as ſheep without a ſhepheard.</hi> He doth not ſay as ſheep without paſture, or ſheep gone aſtray, or ſheep among Wolves, for ſo long as there is a ſhepheard over them, he may provide them paſture, or bring them home into the fold, or drive away the Wolves; but as ſheep without a ſhepheard, in which all theſe miſeries are involv'd: for if the ſhepheard be ſmitten, the ſheep will ſoon be ſcatter'd, and if the ſheep be ſcatter'd, they will ſoon be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs'd for want of paſture, and the Wolves will enter in among them, and there will be none to drive them out. Such is the miſerable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a people that are as ſheep without a ſhepheard: and what is a Church without a Biſhop, but as ſheep without a ſhepheard? The ſame expreſſion is uſed to ſhew the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of a Kingdom without a King. It hath been the ſad condition of this Nation theſe many years to be without both. And yet as if it had been our happineſſe, we have been command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to give thanks to God for that which he would not have ſuffer'd to befall us, if he had not been much offended with us. The Office of a King and the Office of a Biſhop may ſay among us, as Chriſt once ſaid among his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men, <hi>Many a good work have I done among
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115751:22"/>you; for which of theſe do ye ſtone me?</hi> But it is no new thing for men to miſtake their beſt friends for their enemies, and their enemies for their friends; to hate the one, and to fawne upon the other. The Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives us inſtances of both: of the one at <hi>Galatia,</hi> Gal. 4.16. <hi>Am I therefore become your enemy becauſe I tell you the truth?</hi> of the other at <hi>Corinth,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.20. <hi>For ye ſuffer if a man bring you into bondage, if a man devoure you, if a man take of you, if a man exalt himſelf, if a man ſmite you on the face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, God be thanked, we have ſeen the hand of God among us, in gathering us together, to lead us like a flock by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this makes me look back upon my Text, with another reflection of <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> to ſee the good care and circumſpection which is and hath formerly been in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the choice of ſuch men for the Office of a Biſhop as are the moſt <hi>able</hi> and the moſt <hi>likely</hi> to do the Work which belongs to the Office. Wherein I think we are more happy then any Nation in the world. We have read of ſome times and places, in which <hi>novices</hi> have been made Biſhops, becauſe they were the ſons or kinred of <hi>great</hi> men; or ſuch as were able to <hi>purchaſe</hi> this Dignity for them; as the chief Captain obtain'd the priviledg of a Roman <hi>with a great ſumme of money: Boyes</hi> have been taken from the <hi>School</hi> and ſet up in the <hi>chaire,</hi> not ſo glad that they had gotten the Croſier-ſtaff,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115751:22"/>as that they had gotten out of the <hi>reach</hi> of the <hi>Rod.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Laetiores quod virgas evoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, quam quod attingerint principatum.</hi> Bern. <hi>Non iſte ad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopatum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bito pervenit, ſed per omnia eccleſiaſtica officia promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus—ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotii ſublime faſtigium, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis religionis gradibus aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</hi> Cyprian Epiſt. ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonian.</note> But with us the way to the Office of a Biſhop hath been and is the ſame by which St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> that he came to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of <hi>Rome,</hi> not ſuddenly, but by an orderly aſcent through all the inferiour Offices in the Church, as ſo many ſteps and degrees. The way to <hi>purchaſe</hi> the Office of a Biſhop in this Church, is only that of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks in the 13 v. of this <hi>Chap. They who have uſed the Office of a Deacon well, purchaſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a good degree:</hi> ſo it is by having uſed the other Offices in the Church well, that men purchaſe to themſelves this degree, which is the higheſt of them all. And as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſaith, they who would chooſe a fit Pilot to govern a ſhip, doe not chooſe a man becauſe he is the richeſt, or becauſe he is the nobleſt, or becauſe he is the comelieſt perſon among them, but becauſe he is the ableſt and moſt likely to do his work well: ſo it hath been and is the way in chuſing men to ſit at the ſtern in the government of our Church, to make choice of the moſt able and worthy, men who cannot <hi>more</hi> deſire the Office of a Biſhop, then the Office of a Biſhop deſires <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to conclude all in a word. It was ſaid of one of the Emperours, That he got nothing by coming to the Empire but the opportunity of being <hi>able</hi> to doe as much good as he was <hi>willing:</hi> ſo it is the happineſſe of our Church, to ſee ſuch men promoted to the higheſt Office in it, as aime onely at a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115751:23"/>power to doe all the good which they were willing to doe before. And as it is happy for the Church, ſo it is likewiſe happy for them; for though the Work be as <hi>great,</hi> as it is good, the reward will be <hi>greater. For when the chief Shepherd ſhall appear,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.4.</note> ye ſhall receive a crown of Glory that fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115751:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
